YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 3. National Administrative Office
Sophia Smith Collection
- SERIES III. FINANCE AND FINANCIAL DEVELOPMENT
  Financing the National Board, Committee on
  National Support and Interpretation Committee
  World Service Council
  Finance
  Original Format Records, 1907-2002, n.d., 18 linear feet
  With the exception of the Minutes and Reports, there is not a great deal of overlap between the microfilmed materials and the original format records. Both should be consulted.
  The original format records are arranged in 3 Subseries:
  Subseries A. Finance and Development
  Subseries B. Comptroller's Office
  Subseries C. Miscellaneous
  Department/Division and Committees sections include extensive minutes, some general information and correspondence. Included are quite detailed records of the World Service Council.
  Publications contains forms and guidelines associated with National Support/quota payments; manuals and handbooks for training Community Associations about budgeting and fundraising; and an extensive file (including scrapbooks) of financial development pamphlets, booklets, appeal letters, and serial publications.
  Reports contains some general department reports, but the bulk is the remarkable 'visitation' reports written by secretaries and special workers, 1910-20.
  Studies consists of four reports (1946-63) by management consultants on National Association fund-raising.
  Training contains advertising, handouts, presentation materials for workshops on such topics as financial development, money management, planned giving, and proposal writing, dated between 1972 and 1998.
  Fundraising files contain general information about appeals, funds, grants, National Support, and planned/deferred giving. The Campaigns files are records related to the Fund for the Future (1980-86) and extensive files on the Millennium 2000 Campaign (1996-2000). Included are such materials as case statements, donor lists, press kits, prospects files, and reports. The Donors files appear to be files of correspondence with donors that were removed circa 1986 (perhaps because these donors were deceased) from an alphabetical file of large contributors. Similar files can be found on the microfilm.
  Comptroller's Office records include general information about the office, it's areas of responsibility (including budget, accounting, funds, and real estate), practices and procedures. The materials date from 1907 to 2002, but are quite fragmentary. Of special note are records related to YWCA property in China.
  This series consists of a small amount of material about three independent financial organizations established for the benefit of YWCA employees: the Emissarius Credit Union, YWCA Retirement Plan, and YWCA Savings and Security Plan for Non-Secretarial Employees.
  Due to the central nature of the office and its work, Finance and Financial Development materials can be found throughout the National Association records. Key materials can also be found by consulting:
  Publicity/Public Relations materials in SERIES VI of this Record Group
  National Board minutes and reports and Board of Trustees records in RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD
  Convention records in RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONFERENCES AND CONVENTIONS
  Program and Budget Committee minutes in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
  Audio and video presentations about various finance-related subjects, such as development campaigns, the YWCA Retirement Fund, and the National Support Plan are in RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS. There are also audiotapes of selected World Service Council meetings from the late 1970s to 2000.
  See also:
  Regina Bannan, "Management by Women: The First Twenty-Five Years of the YWCA National Board, 1906-31," Ph.D. thesis, University of Pennsylvania, 1994
- SERIES IV. DATA AND STATISTICS
  Initially named "Department for Analysis and Interpretation of Data and Trends," the department was established in 1940 after a two-year trial of a Records and Reports Department in the Laboratory Division. Its proposed charter placed the new department 'within the framework of the principle of long-time planning already adopted by the National Board.' Its task was to assemble and analyze data, ascertain trends within the Association and in the 'social scene' in which the Association operated, and present findings 'in such a way that their meaning can be readily interpreted.'
  Basic information was collected from 'Annual Statistical Report' forms submitted by Community and Student Associations. Data and Trends also carried out studies at the request of various departments, these usually involved the development of questionnaires which were sent out to Associations. Staff of the department also surveyed and reported on trends in other social service, religious, women's, and teen-serving organizations.
  As with most YWCA of the USA departments, Data and Statistics staff also produced written materials and served as consultants for Community and Student Associations in their area of expertise: how to carry out studies and collect data of use to Associations. Guidelines and publications cover such topics as community studies and methods for measuring program costs and effectiveness.
  Over the years, Data and Trends was affiliated with various Association departments, sometimes as part of the department providing services to Community Associations, sometimes with research, sometimes as part of the executive office. In 1972, Association data collection was combined with the central files, library, and (later) archives to form the Data Center. The Data Center (along with the Archives and Library) was eliminated as of September 1992 when national staff was reduced by 50% as a result of staff reorganization and reduction known as Project Redesign. Some of its record-keeping functions were transferred at that time to the Member Association Services Department.
  1940-53 Data and Trends Dept
  1950-53 Data and Statistics (in Membership Resources)
  1954-58 Data and Statistics Dept (in General Administration)
  1959 Research
  1960-61 Bureau of Research, Studies, and Program Resources (in Executive Office)
  1962-72 Bureau of Research and Program Resources
  1972-83 Data Center
  1984-92 Data Center/Management Information Systems
  Data and Statistics records include committee minutes, general material about the department, blank forms, instructional guidelines for Associations and studies, reports, and publications.
  [see Microfilmed Records Reel list]
  Many reports and publications issued from Data and Statistics were filed with other materials related to their subject (for example, reports about camps are on the microfilm under 'Camps.') They are most often included under 'Miscellaneous' at the end of each section.
  Other Data and Statistics materials-mostly department/committee records--can be found on the microfilm under:
  Data and Statistics
  Research and Program Resources
  Original Format Records, 1909-97, 6 linear feet
  Though the department existed from 1940 to 1992, publications containing similar information that both pre-date and post-date the department are filed here to facilitate access. These include: directories of Community and Student YWCAs, directories of Associations with residences, and general statistical compilations (Directory and Statistical Report and Year Book from 1909-19, Hand Book of the YWCA, 1910-19)
  The records are divided into 6 sections: General and History, Committees, Department, Forms and Guidelines, Publications, and Studies and Reports.
  Forms and Guidelines consists of materials related to the development and analysis of the National Association's forms used to assess whether Community and Student Associations' programs meet the "basic standards" for membership in the National Association, as well as the Annual Statistical Report Form. Also included are instructional and training materials for use by Community and Student Associations.
  Publications include annual statistical compilations about Associations and put out by the department and similar earlier publications giving basic statistics about the National Association plus manuals to help Associations analyze program costs.
  Studies and Reports contains research on a wide variety of topics including buildings and facilities, finances, membership, personnel issues, program, racial inclusiveness, and record-keeping.
  Compilation of statistics about the Association was done by the Office Department statistics committee in early years, see Office Department in SERIES I of this Record Group
  Related information and forms can be found in the records of the departments providing direct services to Associations, in RECORD GROUP 8. SERVICES TO COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS.
  For some of its history Data and Statistics was part of the department responsible for research. Records of that department can be found in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM.
  Records of the other departments that made up the Data Center (1972-92), the Library and Archives are in SERIES V. of this Record Group.
  Early statistical report forms were issued through the Publications Department and information about them is available in SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS in RECORD GROUP 6.
- SERIES V. LIBRARY AND ARCHIVES
  Library
  Among the basic services the YWCA of the USA's predecessor Women's and Young Women's Christian Associations provided was easily accessible, free, circulating libraries for women. Given this historical commitment, it was a foregone conclusion that the newly formed National Association would include a historical and reference library in its headquarters building. It was suggested that Miss Schrote of the Office Department, who was a trained librarian, should use a portion of her time to catalog the materials and make recommendations regarding their acquisition. The Office Department was also put in charge of creating exhibits. Though the Library was initially linked in this way with the Association's files, by 1921 administrative responsibility for the collection was moved to the Research Department. The Library remained part of the research function (in Education and Research and then Laboratory Division) until 1939 when it was returned to General Administration under the supervision of Office Services. Here it was part of the Central Filing Bureau which oversaw the central office files, the 'technical and historical files' of YWCA publications, and the Library.
  It was not until 1959 that a full-time Librarian was hired. The Library was moved to the supervision of the Bureau of Research and Program Resources in 1960. As part of the 1971-72 reorganization, the Research and Program Resources Bureau was split in two, with responsibility for program moving to the new Program Development and Public Policy Unit and research moving to the newly established Data Center which consisted of the Library and Central Files. The Library was closed in September 1992 as part of a staff reorganization and reduction known as Project Redesign.
  Archives/Central File/'Record File'
  Maintenance of the files of the National Association was initially the responsibility of the Office Department. As with most of the departments of the YWCA of the USA, the Office Department not only provided services for the National Association, but also served as a model for effective office procedure for Community and Student Associations. A Central File was established and rigorously maintained at least until the 1950s so as to optimize sharing of information across the Association. By 1921, a records retention schedule had been adopted. Records were assigned a retention category (1 year, 2-5 year, or permanent historical) when created, and the files staff was continuously filing and culling to maintain order and facilitate their use. By 1948, space for files was at such a premium that the Office Services Committee began to consider microfilming and discarding older records. In 1950, what had been known as the Central File was renamed the Records Center to correspond with 'the change of terminology in the field.' It was not until 1963 that a decision was made to microfilm some of the records. The first 222 reels of film were made that year, consisting of materials dating from 1899 to 1950 about the predecessor organizations; minutes and reports of the National Board, Board of Trustees, and a few Committees and Departments; Subject Files; and files kept on Community Associations. At the same time, retired YWCA staff member Eleanor Coit, a Smith College alumna, was in the process of donating her personal papers to the Sophia Smith Collection at Smith College. When Coit learned that the records were going to be discarded after microfilming, she approached YWCA Librarian Elizabeth Norris (also a Smith alumna) and the two talked privately with Sophia Smith Collection Director Margaret Grierson about whether Smith College might be interested in preserving some of the materials slated for destruction. As a result of this conversation, selected materials (consisting of 'less than 1/16 of the total') were transferred to Smith in 1964.
  In 1965, the director of the newly-established Social Welfare History Archives Center at the University of Minnesota inquired about preserving the YWCA of the USA records. Since the historical files had by this time been discarded or sent to Smith, the YWCA responded that there was nothing to preserve beyond the microfilm, but agreed to add the SWHA to its mailing list for publications.
  A second, much smaller, batch of materials, was microfilmed in 1968. Included were Subject Files and Community Association Files dating between 1951 and 1960.
  Circa 1974, the Records Center was re-named the 'Records File.'
  Preparations for the U.S. Bicentennial and the growing visibility of women's history, sparked the interest of a couple of National Board members in encouraging Community and Student Associations to preserve their own historical records, and for the national YWCA to help facilitate access to its history. Under the auspices of the Data Center, a questionnaire was sent in December 1974 to all Community and Student Associations asking for information about their historical records. A proposal was submitted to the Program and Budget Committee asking permission to seek outside funding for an Archival Research Project to 'uncover the Grass Roots participation of [the YWCA] in the social development of America.'
  A 1976 grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities resulted in the establishment of the Archives of the YWCA of the USA as a department of the Data Center. It also funded creation of the 1978 "Inventory to the Records Files Collection of the National Board of the Young Women's Christian Association," a guide to the first 282 reels of microfilmed records. The NEH-funded archivist also helped Community Associations with 'sizable historical records' locate suitable repositories for those materials. Prior to the establishment of the Archives department, research access to the YWCA's historical records was by special permission to 'serious students' only. Under the terms of the NEH grant, the records were opened to the public for the first time. The department's holdings initially consisted of the Central (or 'Records') File (including the microfilm), and YWCA publications. Additions to the collection were transferred from Association offices and donated by private individuals.
  After the grant period, Librarian and YWCA Historian Elizabeth Norris, who had been closely involved in the project, took over staffing of the archives in addition to her duties as Librarian. Finding continuing funding proved difficult, however, and the budget which had already reduced the Librarian and YWCA Historian position to part-time, was eliminated and the Archives closed as of September 1992.
  After the sale of the headquarters building in 1982, and the move to much smaller offices, about 35 cubic feet of YWCA/USO files were donated to the Social Welfare History Archives at the University of Minnesota.
  Between 1992 and 2001, the World Service Council provided enough funding to allow for some basic Archives functions to continue, but final decisions about the future of the unit were postponed as the Association endured a lengthy strategic planning process which resulted in a major restructuring in 1999-2000. As part of the celebration of the 135th anniversary of the first YWCA in the U.S., grants were obtained to mount an exhibit of historical materials selected from the Archives and contributed by Community Associations. The exhibit toured the country in 1993-94, but did not result in permanent funding for the Archives. Additional grants were sought without success.
  Once the Association's restructuring was complete, the decision was made to find a repository interested in housing the records. The Sophia Smith Collection was eventually chosen and the records were transferred to Smith College in 2002-03.
  The only related materials on the microfilm are listed under Related Materials below.
  Original Format Records, 1921-2001, n.d., 5.5 linear feet
  [see Original Format Records Folder list]
  The original format records contain general and historical materials about the administration of the Library, Central Files, and Archives. Included are correspondence, memoranda, lists, publications, office forms, research materials, and grant proposals and reports.
  The Archives materials are divided into 6 sections: General and History, Committee/Department, Exhibits, Holdings, Projects, and YWCA History Subject Files. Department administrative records document cooperative relationships with other repositories such as the Sophia Smith Collection and the Social Welfare History Archives; Holdings files document donations to the Archives and transfers from National Association departments. Exhibits and YWCA History Subject Files contain research compiled by Archives staff. The Projects files document various oral histories and publications as well as the National Board Archives Project and various other proposed and funded projects.
  Elsewhere in this Record Group
  The central files were initially the responsibility of the Office Department. Its records can be found in SERIES I.
  The Library and Archives were part of the Data Center (1972-92) with the Data and Statistics Department, its records are in SERIES IV.
  In other Record Groups
  The YWCA's 135th Anniversary Exhibit drew extensively on the resources of the Archives, see also records about the exhibit in RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY.
- SERIES VI. PUBLICITY
  One of the main reasons given for forming a National Association of YWCAs was to centralize the tasks "the associations have found by experience that they can do more effectively together than alone." Among these tasks was "to make the Association known" to the general public and its intended membership. The Publications Department soon began producing a variety of "free literature" about the Association and its program for purposes of "finance cultivation" and general publicity.
  In 1911, the committee overseeing Association publications, which had been informally monitoring press coverage of the Association and managing press coverage of Conventions, urged the National Board to hire a publicity secretary to create an organized publicity program prior to the launch of Capital Funds Campaigns and to take better advantage of upcoming opportunities for publicity, such as the dedication of the new headquarters building. In true YWCA style, a Publicity Committee was formed to consider the question and make recommendations to the National Board. The committee membership (executives of most of the National Association departments with multiple representatives from Finance and Publications departments) reflected the central nature of the work to the Association as a whole-with particular emphasis on its role in financial development. The first Publicity Secretary began work in 1913 under the direction of the Finance Department. Described as "the handmaid of support," publicity remained closely allied with financial development and publications.
  Publicity staff placed general articles in the press about the Association and its programs, such as work with immigrants, Christian work, the National Training School, office efficiency, and foreign work; and sought coverage of special events, such as Conventions, and summer conferences. They looked for opportunities to place items in moving picture newsreels. They developed biographical files on staff and Board members and assembled slides and photographs for lectures, exhibits, and press use. Special projects of the early years included a moving picture about YWCA work for use at the Panama Pacific Exposition in San Francisco in 1915 and art and literary contests held during the Exposition.
  As with most National Association departments, Publicity staff also created manuals and other training materials to teach Community Associations how to do effective publicity. They wrote the 'free literature' available to Community Associations for cultivation of members and fund-raising purposes. And they trained speakers and wrote speakers manuals.
  During World War I, greatly expanded publicity activities were directed by the War Work Council. They were focused mainly on spreading the word about services offered by the YWCA and aiding various fund-raising efforts. The department commissioned a notable series of posters with art work donated to support the war effort. By 1920, with funding from the Continuation Committee, the department employed 29 people in a newspaper section, photographic and moving pictures section, exhibit section, magazine section, printing section, distribution section, and Speakers Bureau. When war-time funds were used up the following year, the staff was cut by nearly two thirds.
  The much-reduced staff continued its efforts through the 1920s, adding advocacy for the National Association's new legislative/public affairs agendas to its activities. Perhaps in response to the National Association's financial woes during the Great Depression, publicity and finance were joined administratively under the Committee for National Support and Interpretation by the mid-1930s. This committee (whose records are filed under Finance and Development) directed all fund-raising, was in charge of securing quota payments from Community Associations, and responsible for "interpretation" of the work of the National Association to the general public.
  The strong tendency of this Committee was to view its interpretation role as "merely an aid to money-raising." By 1942 it was clear that Public Relations' "more elusive…function as a means of creating public confidence in the YWCA aims and activities and increasing the prestige of the National Board had been completely overlooked." A Public Relations Committee was formed which steadily advocated for increased, specialized staff until the National Board Executive Committee voted in May of 1944 to remove 'interpretation to the public' from the role of the National Support and Interpretation Committee and establish a Public Relations Department. (The Committee's name did not reflect this change until its revised charter was approved in 1947.)